<sect1 id="introduction.installation">

    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>
        Zend Framework is built with object-oriented PHP 5 and requires PHP 5.1.4 or later. Please see the
        <link linkend="requirements">system requirements appendix</link> for more detailed information.
    </para>

    <para>
        Once an appropriate PHP environment is available, the next step is to get a copy of the Zend Framework, which
        may be officially obtained by any of the following methods:

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/download/stable">Download the latest stable release.</ulink>
                    This version, available in both <code>.zip</code> and <code>.tar.gz</code> formats, is a good
                    choice for those who are new to Zend Framework.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/download/snapshot">Download the latest nightly
                    snapshot.</ulink> For those who would brave the cutting edge, the nightly snapshots represent the
                    latest progress of Zend Framework development. Snapshots are bundled with documentation either in
                    English only or in all available languages. If you anticipate working with the latest Zend
                    Framework developments, consider using a Subversion (SVN) client.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Using a <ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org">Subversion</ulink> (SVN) client. Zend Framework
                    is open source software, and the Subversion repository used for its development is publicly
                    available. Consider using SVN to get the Zend Framework if you already use SVN for your
                    application development, want to contribute back to the framework, or need to upgrade your
                    framework version more often than releases occur.
                </para>
                <para>
                    <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.export.html">Exporting</ulink> is
                    useful if you want to get a particular framework revision without the <code>.svn</code>
                    directories as created in a working copy.
                </para>
                <para>
                    <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.checkout.html">Checking out a
                    working copy</ulink> is good when you might contribute to Zend Framework, and a working copy can
                    be updated any time with
                    <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.update.html"><code>svn
                    update</code></ulink>.
                </para>
                <para>
                    <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.advanced.externals.html">An externals
                    definition</ulink> is highly convenient for developers already using SVN to manage their
                    application working copies.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The URL for the trunk of the Zend Framework SVN repository is:
                    <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/trunk">http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/trunk</ulink>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
        Once you have a copy of the Zend Framework available, your application needs to be able to access the
        framework classes. Though there are
        <ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/configuration.changes.php">
        several ways to achieve this</ulink>, your PHP
        <ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/ini.core.php#ini.include-path"><code>include_path</code></ulink>
        needs to contain the path to the Zend Framework library.
    </para>

    <para>
        One of the Zend Framework's most useful features is its implementation of the
        <ulink url="http://www.martinfowler.com/eaaCatalog/frontController.html">Front Controller</ulink> and
        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model-view-controller">Model-View-Controller</ulink> (MVC)
        patterns.
        <link linkend="zend.controller.quickstart">Get started with Zend Framework MVC!</link>
    </para>

    <para>
        Since Zend Framework components are rather loosely coupled, various components may be selected for
        independent use as needed. Each of the following chapters documents the use of a particular component.
    </para>

</sect1>
