<sect1 id="zend.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
    The Zend class is the foundation class of the Zend Framework.  This
    class evolved out of the framework's adherence to the DRY principle (Don't Repeat
    Yourself).  It contains only static methods, and these methods
    contain functionality that is required by many components in the Zend Framework.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="zend.loadfile">
    <title>Zend::loadFile()</title>

    <para>
    <code>Zend::loadFile()</code> loads a PHP file, which may contain any PHP code. It is a wrapper for the
    PHP function <ulink url="http://php.net/include"><code>include()</code></ulink> that throws
    <code>Zend_Exception</code> on failure.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
loadFile($filename, $dirs=null, $once=false)]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>The <code>$filename</code> argument specifies the filename to load, which must not contain
    any path information.  A security check is performed on <code>$filename</code>.  The
    <code>$filename</code> may only contain alphanumeric characters, dashes ("-"), underscores ("_"), or
    periods (".").  No such restriction is placed on the <code>$dirs</code> argument.
    </para>

    <para>The <code>$dirs</code> argument specifies directories to search for the file.  If
    <code>NULL</code>, only the <code>include_path</code> will be searched.  If a string
    or an array, the directory or directories specified will be searched, and then the
    <code>include_path</code>.
    </para>

    <para>
    The <code>$once</code> argument is a boolean that specifies whether to use the PHP
    functions <ulink url="http://php.net/include"><code>include()</code></ulink> or <ulink
    url="http://php.net/include_once"><code>include_once()</code></ulink> for loading the file.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="zend.loadclass">
    <title>Zend::loadClass()</title>
    <para>
    <code>Zend::loadClass()</code> loads a PHP file whose filename is formatted like
    "<code>$className.php</code>", and then checks for the existance of the class <code>$className</code>.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
loadClass($class, $dirs)]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
    If the file is not found or the class does not exist after the load, a <code>Zend_Exception</code> is
    thrown. <code>Zend::loadFile()</code> is used for loading, and the <code>$dirs</code> argument is
    passed directly to it..
    </para>

    <para>
    If you ask for a class with underscores in the name, and <code>$dirs</code> is null (the default),
    <code>Zend::loadClass()</code> will auto-discover the <code>$dirs</code> from the class name
    by converting underscores to directory separators.  For example, if <code>$class</code> is
    <code>Zend_Example_Class</code>, that will map to a path of <code>Zend/Example/Class.php</code>.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="zend.loadinterface">
    <title>Zend::loadInterface()</title>
    <para>
    <code>Zend::loadInterface()</code> works exactly the same as <code>Zend::loadClass()</code>, only it
    loads an interface instead.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
loadInterface($interface, $dirs)]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
    The <code>Zend::loadClass()</code> method cannot be used for loading interfaces because the PHP
    function <ulink url="http://php.net/class_exists"><code>class_exists()</code></ulink> does cannot check
    for interfaces (since PHP 5.0.2).  Use <code>Zend::loadInterface()</code> instead.
    </para>

    <para>
    If you ask for an interface with underscores in the name, and <code>$dirs</code> is null (the default),
    <code>Zend::loadInterface()</code> will auto-discover the <code>$dirs</code> from the interface name
    by converting underscores to directory separators.  For example, if <code>$interface</code> is
    <code>Zend_Example_Interface</code>, that will map to a path of <code>Zend/Example/Interface.php</code>.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="zend.isreadable">
    <title>Zend::isReadable()</title>

    <para>Returns <code>TRUE</code> if a file is readable, FALSE otherwise.</para>

    <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
isReadable($filename)]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>The <code>$filename</code> argument specifies the filename to check, which may
    contain path information.  This method is a wrapper for the PHP function
    <ulink url="http://php.net/is_readable"><code>is_readable()</code></ulink>.  The PHP function
    does not search the <code>include_path</code>, while <code>Zend::isReadable()</code> does.
    </para>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="zend.dump">
    <title>Zend::dump()</title>

    <para>
    <code>Zend::dump()</code> prints and/or returns information about an expression.  It is a wrapper
    for the PHP function <ulink url="http://php.net/var_dump"><code>var_dump()</code></ulink>.  It
    wraps the output with (X)HTML <code>&lt;pre&gt;</code> tags and optionally prepends a label.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
dump($var, $label=null, $echo=true)]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
    The <code>$var</code> argument specifies the expression or variable for which the information
    will be obtained.
    </para>

    <para>
    The <code>$label</code> is any arbitrary text to be prepended to the output of
    <code>Zend::dump()</code>.  This is useful when dumping many variables on a single screen.
    </para>

    <para>The boolean <code>$echo</code> controls whether the output of <code>Zend::dump()</code> is echoed
    or not.  If <code>TRUE</code>, the output will be echoed.  Regardless of the state of
    <code>$echo</code>, the output is always be returned.
    </para>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="zend.register">
    <title>Zend::register()</title>

    <para>
    Registers an object in the object store.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
register($name, $object)]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
    The registry is a mechanism for providing singleton instances of objects to the application space.  By
    storing the object in the registry once, and then retrieving the object from the registry whenever it
    is needed, the same instance is always returned.
    </para>

    <para>
    The <code>$name</code> is an arbitrary string to name the object in the store.  This name will be
    supplied to <code>Zend::registry()</code> to retrieve the object again.
    </para>

    <para>
    The <code>$name</code> argument must be a string, only objects may be stored in the registry, an object
    can never be removed from the registry, and an instance can only be stored once in the registry.
    Failure to obey these rules will result in <code>Zend_Exception</code> being thrown.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="zend.registry">
    <title>Zend::registry()</title>

    <para>
    Returns an object in the registry or lists all objects in the registry.
    </para>

    <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
registry($name=null)]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
    If the <code>$name</code> argument is <code>NULL</code>, an array will be returned where the keys to the array
    are the names of the objects in the registry and the values are the class names of those objects.
    </para>

    <para>
    If <code>$name</code> is a string, the object handle assigned to that name will be returned.  If
    an object does not exist in the registry with that <code>$name</code>, a
    <code>Zend_Exception</code> will be thrown.
    </para>
</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->