<sect1 id="zend.session.advancedusage">

    <title>Advanced Usage</title>

    <para>
        While the basic usage examples are a perfectly acceptable way to utilize Zend Framework sessions, there are some
        best practices to consider. Consider the
        <link linkend="zend.auth.introduction.using"><code>Zend_Auth</code> example</link>
        that transparently uses Zend_Session_Namespace by default to persist authentication tokens. This example shows
        one approach to quickly and easily integrate Zend_Session_Namespace and Zend_Auth.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.startingasession">

        <title>Starting a Session</title>

        <para>
            If you want all requests to have a session and use Zend Framework sessions, then start the session in the
            bootstrap file:
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Starting the Global Session</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
...
require_once 'Zend/Session.php';
Zend_Session::start();
...
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            By starting the session in the bootstrap file, you avoid the possibility that your session might be started
            after headers have been sent to the browser, which results in an exception, and possibly a broken page for
            website viewers. Various advanced features require <code>Zend_Session::start()</code> first. (More on
            advanced features later.)
        </para>

        <para>
            There are four ways to start a session, when using Zend_Session. Two are wrong.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    1. Wrong: Do not set PHP's session.auto_start ini setting in either php.ini or .htaccess
                    (http://www.php.net/manual/en/ref.session.php#ini.session.auto-start). If you do not have the
                    ability to disable this setting in php.ini, you are using mod_php (or equivalent), and the setting
                    is already enabled in php.ini, then add <code>php_value session.auto_start 0</code> to your
                    .htaccess file (usually in your HTML document root directory).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    2. Wrong: Do not use PHP's <code>
                    <ulink url="http://www.php.net/session_start">session_start()</ulink>
                    </code> function directly. If you use <code>session_start()</code> directly, and then start using
                    Zend_Session_Namespace, an exception will be thrown by <code>Zend_Session::start()</code> ("session
                    has already been started"). If you call <code>session_start()</code>, after using
                    Zend_Session_Namespace or starting <code>Zend_Session::start()</code> explicitly, an error of level
                    E_NOTICE will be generated, and the call will be ignored.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    3. Correct: Use <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>. If you want all requests to have and use
                    sessions, then place this function call early and unconditionally in your ZF bootstrap code.
                    Sessions have some overhead. If some requests need sessions, but other requests will not need to use
                    sessions, then:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Unconditionally, set the <code>strict</code> option to true (see
                            <link
                        linkend="zend.session.startingasession"><code>Zend_Session::setOptions()</code>
                            </link>
                            ) in your userland bootstrap.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Call <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>, only for requests that need to use sessions, before
                            the first call to <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace()</code>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Use <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace()</code> normally, where needed, but make sure
                            <code>Zend_Session::start()</code> has been called previously.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>
                    The <code>strict</code> option prevents <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace()</code> from automatically
                    starting the session using <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>. Thus, this option helps developers of
                    userland ZF applications enforce a design decision to avoid using sessions for certain requests,
                    since an error will be thrown when using this option and instantiating Zend_Session_Namespace,
                    before an explicit call to <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>. Do not use this option in ZF core
                    library code, because only userland developers should make this design choice. Similarly, all
                    "library" developers should carefully consider the impact of using
                    <code>Zend_Session::setOptions()</code> on users of their library code, since these options have
                    global side-effects (as do the underlying options for ext/session).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    4. Correct: Just use <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace()</code> whenever needed, and the session will
                    be automatically started within Zend_Session. This offers extremely simple usage that works well in
                    most situations. However, you then become responsible for ensuring that the first <code>new
                    Zend_Session_Namespace()</code> happens <emphasis role="strong">before</emphasis> any output (i.e.
                    <ulink url="http://www.php.net/headers_sent">HTTP headers</ulink>
                    ) has been sent by PHP to the client, if you are using the default, cookie-based sessions (strongly
                    recommended). See
                    <xref linkend="zend.session.errors.headerssent" />
                    for more information.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.locking">

        <title>Locking Session Namespaces</title>

        <para>
            Session namespaces can be locked, to prevent further alterations to the data in that namespace. Use
            <code>Zend_Session_Namespace's lock()</code> to make a specific namespace read-only, <code>unLock()</code>
            to make a read-only namespace read-write, and <code>isLocked()</code> to test if a namespace has been
            previously locked. Locks are transient and do not persist from one request to the next. Locking the
            namespace has no effect on setter methods of objects stored in the namespace, but does prevent the use of
            the namespace's setter method to remove or replace objects stored directly in the namespace. Similarly,
            locking Zend_Session_Namespace namespaces does not prevent the use of symbol table aliases to the same data
            (see
            <ulink url="http://www.php.net/references">PHP references</ulink>
            ).
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Locking Session Namespaces</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    // assuming:
    $userProfileNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('userProfileNamespace');

    // marking session as read only locked
    $userProfileNamespace->lock();

    // unlocking read-only lock
    if ($userProfileNamespace->isLocked()) {
        $userProfileNamespace->unLock();
    }
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            There are numerous ideas for how to manage models in MVC paradigms for the Web, including creating
            presentation models for use by views. Sometimes existing data, whether part of your domain model or not, is
            adequate for the task. To discourage views from applying any processing logic to alter such data, consider
            locking session namespaces before permitting views to access this subset of your "presentation" model.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Locking Sessions in Views</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
class FooModule_View extends Zend_View
{
    public function show($name)
    {
        if (!isset($this->mySessionNamespace)) {
            $this->mySessionNamespace = Zend::registry('FooModule');
        }

        if ($this->mySessionNamespace->isLocked()) {
            return parent::render($name);
        }

        $this->mySessionNamespace->lock();
        $return = parent::render($name);
        $this->mySessionNamespace->unLock();

        return $return;
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.expiration">

        <title>Namespace Expiration</title>

        <para>
            Limits can be placed on the longevity of both namespaces and individual keys in namespaces. Common use cases
            include passing temporary information between requests, and reducing exposure to certain security risks by
            removing access to potentially sensitive information some time after authentication occurred. Expiration can
            be based on elapsed seconds, or based on the concept of "hops", where a hop occurs for each successive
            request that activates the namespace via at least one <code>$space = new
            Zend_Session_Namespace('myspace');</code>.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Expiration Examples</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
$s = new Zend_Session_Namespace('expireAll');
$s->a = 'apple';
$s->p = 'pear';
$s->o = 'orange';

$s->setExpirationSeconds(5, 'a'); // expire only the key "a" in 5 seconds

// expire entire namespace in 5 "hops"
$s->setExpirationHops(5);

$s->setExpirationSeconds(60);
// The "expireAll" namespace will be marked "expired" on
// the first request received after 60 seconds have elapsed,
// or in 5 hops, whichever happens first.
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            When working with data expiring from the session in the current request, care should be used when retrieving
            it. Although the data is returned by reference, modifying the data will not make expiring data persist past
            the current request. In order to "reset" the expiration time, fetch the data into temporary variables, use
            the namespace to unset it, and then set the appropriate keys again.
        </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.controllers">

        <title>Session Encapsulation and Controllers</title>

        <para>
            Namespaces can also be used to separate session access by controllers to protect variables from
            contamination. For example, the 'Zend_Auth' controller might keep its session state data separate from all
            other controllers.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Namespaced Sessions for Controllers with Automatic Expiration</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
require_once 'Zend/Session.php';
// question view controller
$testSpace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('testSpace');
$testSpace->setExpirationSeconds(300, "accept_answer"); // expire only this variable
$testSpace->accept_answer = true;

--

// answer processing controller
$testSpace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('testSpace');

if ($testSpace->accept_answer === true) {
    // within time
}
else {
    // not within time
}
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.limitinginstances">

        <title>Limiting Instances of Zend_Session_Namespace to One Per Namespace</title>

        <para>
            We recommend using session locking (see above) instead of the feature below, which places extra management
            burden on the developer to pass any Zend_Session_Namespace instances into whatever functions and objects
            need access to each namespace.
        </para>

        <para>
            When constructing the first instance of Zend_Session_Namespace attached to a specific namespace, you can
            also instruct Zend_Session_Namespace to not make any more instances for that namespace. Thus, any future
            attempts to construct a Zend_Session_Namespace instance having the same namespace will throw an error. Such
            behavior is optional, and not the default behavior, but remains available to those who prefer to pass around
            a single instance object for each namespace. This increases protection from changes by components that
            should not modify a particular session namespace, because they won't have easy access. However, limiting a
            namespace to a single instance may lead to more code or more complex code, as it removes access to the
            convient <code>$aNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('aNamespace');</code>, after the first intance has
            been created, as follows in the example below:
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Limiting to Single Instances</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    require_once 'Zend/Session.php';
    $authSpaceAccessor1 = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth');
    $authSpaceAccessor2 = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth', Zend_Session_Namespace::SINGLE_INSTANCE);
    $authSpaceAccessor1->foo = 'bar';
    assert($authSpaceAccessor2->foo, 'bar'); // passes
    doSomething($options, $authSpaceAccessor2); // pass the accessor to wherever it is needed
    .
    .
    .
    $aNamespaceObject = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth'); // this will throw an error
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            The second parameter in the constructor above will tell Zend_Session_Namespace that any future
            Zend_Session's that are instantiated with the 'Zend_Auth' namespace are not allowed, and will thus cause an
            exception. Since <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth')</code> will not be allowed after the code
            above has been executed, the developer becomes responsible for storing the instance object
            (<code>$authSpaceAccessor2</code> in the example above) somewhere, if access to this session namespace is
            needed at a later time during the same request. For example, a developer may store the instance in a static
            variable, or pass it to other methods that might need access to this session namespace. Session locking (see
            above) provides a more convenient, and less burdensome approach to limiting access to namespaces.
        </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.modifyingarray">

        <title>Working with Arrays in Namespaces</title>

        <para>
            Modifying an array inside a namespace does not work. The simplest solution is to store arrays after all
            desired values have been set.
            <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/issues/browse/ZF-800">ZF-800</ulink>
            documents a known issue affecting many PHP applications using magic methods and arrays.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Known problem with arrays</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    $sessionNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Foo');
    $sessionNamespace->array = array();
    $sessionNamespace->array['testKey'] = 1; // does not work before PHP 5.2.1
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            If you need to modify the array after assigning it to a session namespace key, fetch the array, then
            modify it and save the array back to the session namespace.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Workaround: fetch, modify, save</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    $sessionNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Foo');
    $sessionNamespace->array = array('tree' => 'apple');
    $tmp = $sessionNamespace->array;
    $tmp['fruit'] = 'peach';
    $sessionNamespace->array = $tmp;
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            Alternatively, store an array containing a reference to the desired array, and then access it indirectly.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Workaround: store array containing reference</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    $myNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('mySpace');

    // works, even for broken versions of PHP
    $a = array(1,2,3);
    $myNamespace->someArray = array( & $a ) ;
    $a['foo'] = 'bar';
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.auth">

        <title>Using Sessions with Authentication</title>

        <para>
            If your authentication adapter for <code>Zend_Auth</code> returns a result where the authorization identity
            is an object (not recommended), instead of an array, then make sure to require your authorization identity
            class definition before starting the session. Instead, we recommend storing the authorization ids computed
            within an authentication adapter inside a well-known key in a session namespace. For example, the default
            behavior of <code>Zend_Auth</code> places this in the 'storage' key of the 'Zend_Auth' namespace.
        </para>

        <para>
            If you tell <code>Zend_Auth</code> to not persist authentication tokens in sessions, then you can manually
            store the authorization id in the session namespace, in a well-known location in a session namespace of your
            choice. Often, applications have specific needs about where to store credentials used (if any) and
            "authorization" identity. Applications often map authentication identities (e.g. usernames) to authorization
            identities (e.g. a uniquely assigned integer) during authentication, which would occur in the Zend_Auth
            authentication adapter's <code>authenticate()</code> method.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Example: Simplified access of authorization ids</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    // pre-authentication request
    require_once 'Zend/Auth/Adapter/Digest.php';
    $adapter = new Zend_Auth_Adapter_Digest($filename, $realm, $username, $password);
    $result = $adapter->authenticate();
    require_once 'Zend/Session/Namespace.php';
    $namespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth');
    if ($result->isValid()) {
        $namespace->authorizationId = $result->getIdentity();
        $namespace->date = time();
    } else {
        $namespace->attempts++;
    }

    // subsequent requests
    require_once 'Zend/Session.php';
    Zend_Session::start();
    $namespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth');

    echo "Valid: ", (empty($namespace->authorizationId) ? 'No' : 'Yes'), "\n"';
    echo "Authorization / user Id: ", (empty($namespace->authorizationId)
        ? 'none' : print_r($namespace->authorizationId, true)), "\n"';
    echo "Authentication attempts: ", (empty($namespace->attempts)
        ? '0' : $namespace->attempts), "\n"';
    echo "Authenticated on: ",
        (empty($namespace->date) ? 'No' : date(DATE_ATOM, $namespace->date), "\n"';
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            Authorization ids stored client-side are subject to privilege escalation vulnerabilities, if these ids are
            used and trusted by the server, unless, for example, the id is duplicated on the server-side (e.g. in the
            session) and then cross-checked with the authorization id claimed by the client for the in-effect session.
            We are differentiating between "authentication ids" (e.g. usernames) and "authorization ids" (e.g. user id
            #101 in the users DB table).
        </para>

        <para>
            The latter is not uncommon for performance reasons, such as helping select from a pool of servers caching
            session information to help solve chicken-and-egg problems. Often debates ensue about whether to use the
            real authorization id in the cookie, or some substitute that aids in mapping to the real authorization id
            (or session or server(s) holding the user's session/profile, etc.), as some system security architects wish
            to prevent true "DB primary keys" from escaping into the wild. These architects try and obtain some level of
            protection by obfuscation in the event of a SQL injection vulnerability in their system. Not everyone uses
            auto-increment strategies for authorization ids.
        </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.testing">

        <title>Using Sessions with Unit Tests</title>

        <para>
            The Zend Framework relies on PHPUnit to facilitate testing of itself. Many developers extend the existing
            suite of unit tests to cover the code in their applications. The exception
            "<emphasis role="strong">Zend_Session is currently marked as read-only</emphasis>" is thrown while
            performing unit tests, if any write-related methods are used after ending the session. However, unit tests
            using Zend_Session require extra attention, because closing (<code>Zend_Session::writeClose()</code>), or
            destroying a session (<code>Zend_Session::destroy()</code>) prevents any further setting or unsetting of
            keys in any Zend_Session_Namespace. This behavior is a direct result of the underlying ext/session mechanism
            and PHP's <code>session_destroy()</code> and <code>session_write_close()</code>, which has no "undo"
            mechanism to facilitate setup/teardown with unit tests.
        </para>

        <para>
            To work around this, see the unit test <code>testSetExpirationSeconds()</code> in
            <code>tests/Zend/Session/SessionTest.php and SessionTestHelper.php</code>, which make use of PHP's
            <code>exec()</code> to launch a separate process. The new process more accurately simulates a second,
            successive request from a browser. The separate process begins with a "clean" session, just like any PHP
            script execution for a web request. Also, any changes to <code>$_SESSION[]</code> made in the calling
            process become available to the child process, provided the parent closed the session before using
            <code>exec()</code>
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Using PHPUnit to test code written using Zend_Session*</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
        // testing setExpirationSeconds()
        require 'tests/Zend/Session/SessionTestHelper.php'; // also see SessionTest.php in trunk/
        $script = 'SessionTestHelper.php';
        $s = new Zend_Session_Namespace('space');
        $s->a = 'apple';
        $s->o = 'orange';
        $s->setExpirationSeconds(5);

        Zend_Session::regenerateId();
        $id = Zend_Session::getId();
        session_write_close(); // release session so process below can use it
        sleep(4); // not long enough for things to expire
        exec($script . "expireAll $id expireAll", $result);
        $result = $this->sortResult($result);
        $expect = ';a === apple;o === orange;p === pear';
        $this->assertTrue($result === $expect,
            "iteration over default Zend_Session namespace failed; expecting result === '$expect', but got '$result'");

        sleep(2); // long enough for things to expire (total of 6 seconds waiting, but expires in 5)
        exec($script . "expireAll $id expireAll", $result);
        $result = array_pop($result);
        $this->assertTrue($result === '',
            "iteration over default Zend_Session namespace failed; expecting result === '', but got '$result')");
        session_start(); // resume artificially suspended session

        // We could split this into a separate test, but actually, if anything leftover from above
        // contaminates the tests below, that is also a bug that we want to know about.
        $s = new Zend_Session_Namespace('expireGuava');
        $s->setExpirationSeconds(5, 'g'); // now try to expire only 1 of the keys in the namespace
        $s->g = 'guava';
        $s->p = 'peach';
        $s->p = 'plum';

        session_write_close(); // release session so process below can use it
        sleep(6); // not long enough for things to expire
        exec($script . "expireAll $id expireGuava", $result);
        $result = $this->sortResult($result);
        session_start(); // resume artificially suspended session
        $this->assertTrue($result === ';p === plum',
            "iteration over named Zend_Session namespace failed (result=$result)");
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

</sect1>
