<sect1 id="zend.controller.action">
	<title>Action Controllers</title>

	<sect2 id="zend.controller.action.introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
            <code>Zend_Controller_Action</code> is an abstract class you may use
            for implementing Action Controllers for use with the Front
            Controller when building a website based on the
            Model-View-Controller (MVC) pattern.
		</para>

		<para>
            To use Zend_Controller_Action, you will need to subclass it in your
            actual action controllers (or subclass it to create your own base
            class for action controllers). The most basic operation is to
            subclass it, and create action methods that correspond to the
            various actions you wish the controller to handle for your site.
            Zend_Controller's routing and dispatch handling will autodiscover
            any methods ending in 'Action' in your class as potential
            controller actions.
        </para>

        <para>
            For example, let's say your class is defined as follows:
        </para>

        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
class FooController extends Zend_Controller_Action
{
    public function barAction()
    {
        // do something
    }

    public function bazAction()
    {
        // do something
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
            
        <para>
            The above FooController class (controller 'foo') defines two
            actions, 'bar' and 'baz'.
        </para>

        <para>
            There's much more that can be accomplished than this, such as custom
            initialization actions, default actions to call should no action (or
            an invalid action) be specified, pre- and post-dispatch hooks, and a
            variety of helper methods. This chapter serves as an overview of the
            action controller functionality
        </para>
    </sect2>

	<sect2 id="zend.controller.action.initialization">
        <title>Object initialization</title>

        <para>
            While you can always override the action controller's constructor,
            we do not recommend this. Zend_Controller_Action::__construct()
            performs some important tasks, such as registring the request and
            response objects, as well as any custom invocation arguments passed
            in from the front controller. If you must override the constructor,
            be sure to call parent::__construct($request, $response,
            $invokeArgs).
        </para>

        <para>
            The more appropriate way to customize instantiation is to use the
            init() method, which is called as the last task of __construct().
            For example, if you want to connect to a database at instantiation:
        </para>

        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
class FooController extends Zend_Controller_Action
{
    public function init()
    {
        $this->db = Zend_Db::factory('Pdo_Mysql', array(
            'host'     => 'myhost',
            'username' => 'user',
            'password' => 'XXXXXXX',
            'dbname'   => 'website'
        ));
    }
}
]]></programlisting>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.controller.action.prepostdispatch">
        <title>Pre- and Post-Dispatch Hooks</title>

        <para>
            Zend_Controller_Action specifies two methods that may be called to
            bookend a requested action, preDispatch() and postDispatch(). These
            can be useful in a variety of ways: verifying authentication and
            ACLs prior to running an action (by calling _forward() in
            preDispatch(), the action will be skipped), for instance, or placing
            generated content in a sitewide template (postDispatch()).
        </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.controller.action.accessors">
        <title>Accessors</title>

        <para>
            A number of objects and variables are registered with the object,
            and each has accessor methods.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>
                <emphasis>Request Object</emphasis>: getRequest() may be
                used to retrieve the request object used to call the action.
            </para></listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Response Object</emphasis>: getResponse() may be
                    used to retrieve the response object aggregating the final
                    response. Some typical calls might look like:
                </para>

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
$this->getResponse()->setHeader('Content-Type', 'text/xml');
$this->getResponse()->appendBody($content);
]]></programlisting>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Invocation Arguments</emphasis>: the front
                    controller may push parameters into the router, dispatcher,
                    and action controller. To retrieve these, use
                    getInvokeArg($key); alternatively, fetch the entire list
                    using getInvokeArgs().
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Request parameters</emphasis>: The request object
                    aggregates request parameters, such as any _GET or _POST
                    parameters, or user parameters specified in the URL's path
                    information. To retrieve these, use _getParam($key) or
                    _getAllParams(). You may also set request parameters using
                    _setParam(); this is useful when forwarding to additional
                    actions.
                </para>

                <para>
                    To test whether or not a parameter exists (useful for
                    logical branching), use _hasParam($key).
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.controller.action.utilmethods">
        <title>Utility Methods</title>

        <para>
            Besides the accessors, Zend_Controller_Action has several utility
            methods for performing common tasks from within your action methods
            (or from pre-/post-dispatch).
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>_forward($action, $controller = null, $module =
                        null, array $params = null)</emphasis>: 
                    perform another action. If called in preDispatch(), the
                    currently requested action will be skipped in favor of the
                    new one. Otherwise, after the current action is processed,
                    the action requested in _forward() will be executed.
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>_redirect($url, $code = 302)</emphasis>: redirect
                    to another location. This method takes a URL and an optional
                    HTTP status code. The redirect is performed immediately and
                    program execution is halted.
                </para>

                <para>
                    If a status code is provided, it will be passed to the PHP
                    header() command when the redirect is performed.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
</sect1>

<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
