    <sect1 id="coding-standard.naming-conventions">
        <title>Naming Conventions</title>

        <sect2 id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.classes">
            <title>Classes</title>

            <para>
                The Zend Framework employs a class naming convention whereby the names
                of the classes directly map to the directories in which they are stored.
                The root level directory of the Zend Framework is the "Zend/" directory,
                under which all classes are stored hierarchially.
            </para>

            <para>
                Class names may only contain alphanumeric characters.   Numbers are permitted
                in class names but are discouraged.  Underscores are only permitted in place
                of the path separator -- the filename "Zend/Db/Table.php" must map to the
                class name "Zend_Db_Table".
            </para>

            <para>
                If a class name is comprised of more than one word, the first letter of each new
                word must be capitalized.  Successive capitalized letters are not allowed, e.g.
                a class "Zend_PDF" is not allowed while "Zend_Pdf" is acceptable.
            </para>

            <para>
                Zend Framework classes that are authored by Zend or one of the participating
                partner companies and distributed with the Framework must always start with
                "Zend_" and must be stored under the "Zend/" directory hierarchy accordingly.
            </para>

            <para>
                These are examples of acceptable names for classes:

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
Zend_Db

Zend_View

Zend_View_Helper
]]></programlisting>

                <emphasis>IMPORTANT:</emphasis> Code that operates with the framework but is not
                part of the framework, e.g. code written by a framework end-user and not Zend or
                one of the framework's partner companies, must never start with "Zend_".
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.interfaces">
            <title>Interfaces</title>

            <para>
                Interface classes must follow the same conventions as other classes (see above),
                however must end with the word "Interface", such as in these examples:

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
Zend_Log_Adapter_Interface
Zend_Controller_Dispatcher_Interface]]></programlisting>
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.filenames">
            <title>Filenames</title>

            <para>
                For all other files, only alphanumeric characters, underscores, and the dash
                character ("-") are permitted. Spaces and are prohibited.
            </para>

            <para>
                Any file that contains any PHP code must end with the extension ".php". These
                examples show the acceptable filenames for containing the class names from the
                examples in the section above:

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
Zend/Db.php

Zend/Controller/Front.php

Zend/View/Helper/FormRadio.php]]></programlisting>

                File names must follow the mapping to class names described above.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.functions-and-methods">
            <title>Functions and Methods</title>

            <para>
                Function names may only contain alphanumeric characters. Underscores are not permitted.
                Numbers are permitted in function names but are discouraged.
            </para>

            <para>
                Function names must always start with a lowercase letter. When a function name consists
                of more than one word, the first letter of each new word must be capitalized. This is
                commonly called the "camelCaps" method.
            </para>

            <para>
                Verbosity is encouraged. Function names should be as verbose as is practical to enhance the
                understandability of code.
            </para>

            <para>
                These are examples of acceptable names for functions:

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
filterInput()

getElementById()

widgetFactory()]]></programlisting>
            </para>

            <para>
                For object-oriented programming, accessors for objects should always be prefixed with
                either "get" or "set". When using design patterns, such as the singleton or factory
                patterns, the name of the method should contain the pattern name where practical to
                make the pattern more readily recognizable.
            </para>

            <para>
                Functions in the global scope ("floating functions") are permitted but discouraged.
                It is recommended that these functions should be wrapped in a static class.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.variables">
            <title>Variables</title>

            <para>
                Variable names may only contain alphanumeric characters. Underscores are not permitted.
                Numbers are permitted in variable names but are discouraged.
            </para>

            <para>
                For class member variables that are declared with the "private" or "protected" construct,
                the first character of the function name must be a single underscore. This is the only
                acceptable usage of an underscore in a function name. Member variables declared "public"
                may never start with an underscore.
            </para>

            <para>
                Like function names (see section 3.3, above) variable names must always start with a
                lowercase letter and follow the "camelCaps" capitalization convention.
            </para>

            <para>
                Verbosity is encouraged. Variables should always be as verbose as practical. Terse variable
                names such as "$i" and "$n" are discouraged for anything other than the smallest loop contexts.
                If a loop contains more than 20 lines of code, the variables for the indices need to have more
                descriptive names.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="coding-standard.naming-conventions.constants">
            <title>Constants</title>

            <para>
                Constants may contain both alphanumeric characters and the underscore. Numbers are permitted
                in constant names.
            </para>

            <para>
                Constants must always have all letters capitalized.
            </para>

            <para>
                Constants must be defined as class members by using the "const" construct. Defining constants
                in the global scope with "define" is permitted but discouraged.
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
