<sect1 id="zend.session.advancedusage">

    <title>Użycie zaawansowane</title>

    <para>
        Chociaż przykłady podstawowego użycia sesji są całkowicie zadowalającym
        sposobem wykorzystania sesji Zend Framework, to jest kilka dobrych
        zwyczajów, ktore powinieneś przeanalizować. Przeanalizuj 
        <link linkend="zend.auth.introduction.using">przykład użycia <code>Zend_Auth</code></link>,
        który domyślnie używa Zend_Session_Namespace do przechowywania
        danych uwierzytelniania. Ten przykład pokazuje jeden sposób szybkiego i 
        łatwego zintegrowania Zend_Session_Namespace oraz Zend_Auth.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.startingasession">

        <title>Rozpoczynanie sesji</title>

        <para>
            Jeśli chcesz aby wszystkie żądania używały sesji i używały sesji
            Zend Framework, to rozpocznik sesję w pliku ładującym:
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Rozpoczynanie globalnej sesji</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
...
require_once 'Zend/Session.php';
Zend_Session::start();
...
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            Rozpoczynając sesję w pliku ładującym zapobiegasz przypadkowym
            próbom rozpoczęcia sesji po wysłaniu nagłówków do przeglądarki, 
            co powodowałoby wyrzucenie wyjątku i prawdopodobnie wyświetlenie
            nieprawidłowo wygenerowanej strony. Wiele zaawansowanych 
            funkcjonalności wymaga wcześniejszego wywołania metody 
            <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>. (więcej informacji o 
            zaawansowanych funkcjonalnościach pojawi się później)
        </para>

        <para>
            Są cztery sposoby rozpoczęcia sesji, gdy używamy Zend_Session. Dwa
            z nich są złe.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    1. Źle: Nie ustawiaj parametru PHP session.auto_start w pliku
                    php.ini lub .htaccess
                    (http://www.php.net/manual/en/ref.session.php#ini.session.auto-start). 
                    Jeśli nie masz możliwości zablokowania tego parametru w 
                    pliku php.ini, a używasz modułu mod_php (lub jego odpowiednika), 
                    a ustawienie to jest obecnie włączone w pliku php.ini, to 
                    dodaj <code>php_value session.auto_start 0</code> w twoim 
                    pliku .htaccess (najczęściej w twoim głównym katalogu serwera).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    2. Źle: Nie używaj bezpośrednio funkcji PHP <code>
                    <ulink url="http://www.php.net/session_start">session_start()</ulink>
                    </code>. Jeśli użyjesz funkcji <code>session_start()</code> 
                    bezpośrednio, a potem rozpoczniesz sesję używając obiektu 
                    Zend_Session_Namespace, metoda <code>Zend_Session::start()</code> 
                    wyrzuci wyjątek ("session has already been started"). 
                    Jeśli wywołasz funkcję <code>session_start()</code>, po 
                    użyciu obiektu Zend_Session_Namespace lub po rozpoczęciu
                    sesji za pomocą metody <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>, 
                    zostanie wygenerowany błąd poziomu E_NOTICE, a wywołanie
                    funkcji zostanie zignorowane.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    3. Dobrze: Użyj <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>. Jeśli 
                    chcesz aby wszystkie żądania używały sesji, bezwarunkowo 
                    umieść wywołanie tej funkcji na początku, w twoim pliku 
                    ładującym ZF. 
                    Sessions have some overhead. If some requests need 
                    sessions, but other requests will not need to use sessions, 
                    then:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Unconditionally, set the <code>strict</code> option 
                            to true (zobacz <link
                        linkend="zend.session.startingasession"><code>Zend_Session::setOptions()</code>
                            </link>) in your userland bootstrap.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Wywołaj metodę <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>,
                            tylko dla żądań, które potrzebują użyć sesji, zanim
                            pierwszy raz wywołasz metodę
                            <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace()</code>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Użyj <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace()</code>,
                            normalnie, wtedy gdy będzie to potrzebne, ale upewnij
                            się, że wcześniej zostanie wywołana metoda 
                            <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>
                    Opcja <code>strict</code> zapobiega automatycznemu
                    rozpoczęciu sesji za pomocą metody
                    <code>Zend_Session::start()</code> w konstruktorze 
                    <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace()</code>.
                    Thus, this option helps developers of userland ZF applications 
                    enforce a design decision to avoid using sessions for certain 
                    requests, since an error will be thrown when using this option 
                    and instantiating Zend_Session_Namespace, before an explicit 
                    call to <code>Zend_Session::start()</code>. Do not use this 
                    option in ZF core library code, because only userland 
                    developers should make this design choice. Similarly, all
                    "library" developers should carefully consider the impact of 
                    using <code>Zend_Session::setOptions()</code> on users of 
                    their library code, since these options have global 
                    side-effects (as do the underlying options for ext/session).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    4. Dobrze: Po prostu użyj <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace()</code> 
                    kiedy tylko będziesz potrzebował, a sesja zostanie automatycznie
                    rozpoczęta przez Zend_Session. To pozwala na ekstremalnie
                    proste użycie, działające w większości sytuacji.
                    However, you then become responsible for ensuring that the 
                    first <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace()</code> happens 
                    <emphasis role="strong">before</emphasis> any output (i.e.
                    <ulink url="http://www.php.net/headers_sent">HTTP headers</ulink>
                    ) has been sent by PHP to the client, if you are using the 
                    default, cookie-based sessions (strongly recommended). See
                    <xref linkend="zend.session.errors.headerssent" />
                    for more information.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.locking">

        <title>Blokowanie przestrzeni nazw sesji</title>

        <para>
            Session namespaces can be locked, to prevent further alterations to 
            the data in that namespace. Use <code>Zend_Session_Namespace's lock()</code> 
            to make a specific namespace read-only, <code>unLock()</code> to 
            make a read-only namespace read-write, and <code>isLocked()</code> 
            to test if a namespace has been previously locked. Locks are 
            transient and do not persist from one request to the next. Locking 
            the namespace has no effect on setter methods of objects stored in 
            the namespace, but does prevent the use of the namespace's setter 
            method to remove or replace objects stored directly in the namespace. 
            Similarly, locking Zend_Session_Namespace namespaces does not prevent 
            the use of symbol table aliases to the same data (see
            <ulink url="http://www.php.net/references">PHP references</ulink>).
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Blokowanie przestrzeni nazw sesji</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    // zakładając:
    $userProfileNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('userProfileNamespace');

    // oznaczanie sesji jako zablokowanej tylko do odczytu
    $userProfileNamespace->lock();

    // odblokowanie sesji
    if ($userProfileNamespace->isLocked()) {
        $userProfileNamespace->unLock();
    }
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            There are numerous ideas for how to manage models in MVC paradigms 
            for the Web, including creating presentation models for use by 
            views. Sometimes existing data, whether part of your domain model or 
            not, is adequate for the task. To discourage views from applying any 
            processing logic to alter such data, consider locking session 
            namespaces before permitting views to access this subset of your 
            "presentation" model.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Blokowanie danych sesji w widokach</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
class FooModule_View extends Zend_View
{
    public function show($name)
    {
        if (!isset($this->mySessionNamespace)) {
            $this->mySessionNamespace = Zend::registry('FooModule');
        }

        if ($this->mySessionNamespace->isLocked()) {
            return parent::render($name);
        }

        $this->mySessionNamespace->lock();
        $return = parent::render($name);
        $this->mySessionNamespace->unLock();

        return $return;
    }
}
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.expiration">

        <title>Namespace Expiration</title>

        <para>
            Limits can be placed on the longevity of both namespaces and individual keys in namespaces.
            Common use cases include passing temporary information between requests, and reducing exposure
            to certain security risks by removing access to potentially sensitive information some time
            after authentication occurred.  Expiration can be based on elapsed seconds, or based on
            the concept of "hops", where a hop occurs for each successive request that activates the
            namespace via at least one <code>$space = new Zend_Session_Namespace('myspace');</code>.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Expiration Examples</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
$s = new Zend_Session_Namespace('expireAll');
$s->a = 'apple';
$s->p = 'pear';
$s->o = 'orange';

$s->setExpirationSeconds(5, 'a'); // expire only the key "a" in 5 seconds

// expire entire namespace in 5 "hops"
$s->setExpirationHops(5);

$s->setExpirationSeconds(60);                  
// The "expireAll" namespace will be marked "expired" on
// the first request received after 60 seconds have elapsed,
// or in 5 hops, whichever happens first.
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            When working with data expiring from the session in the current request,
            care should be used when retrieving it.  Although the data is returned by reference,
            modifying the data will not make expiring data persist past the current request.
            In order to "reset" the expiration time, fetch the data into temporary variables,
            use the namespace to unset it, and then set the appropriate keys again.
        </para>

    </sect2>


    <sect2 id="zend.session.controllers">

        <title>Session Encapsulation and Controllers</title>

        <para>
            Namespaces can also be used to separate session access by 
            controllers to protect variables from contamination. For example, 
            the 'Zend_Auth' controller might keep its session state data 
            separate from all other controllers.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Namespaced Sessions for Controllers with Automatic Expiration</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
require_once 'Zend/Session.php';
// question view controller
$testSpace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('testSpace');
$testSpace->setExpirationSeconds(300, "accept_answer"); // expire only this variable
$testSpace->accept_answer = true;

-- 

// answer processing controller
$testSpace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('testSpace');

if ($testSpace->accept_answer === true) {
    // within time
}
else {
    // not within time
}
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.limitinginstances">

        <title>Limiting Instances of Zend_Session_Namespace to One Per Namespace</title>

        <para>
            We recommend using session locking (see above) instead of the feature below, which places extra management
            burden on the developer to pass any Zend_Session_Namespace instances into whatever functions and objects
            need access to each namespace.
        </para>

        <para>
            When constructing the first instance of Zend_Session_Namespace attached to a specific namespace, you can
            also instruct Zend_Session_Namespace to not make any more instances for that namespace. Thus, any future
            attempts to construct a Zend_Session_Namespace instance having the same namespace will throw an error. Such
            behavior is optional, and not the default behavior, but remains available to those who prefer to pass around
            a single instance object for each namespace. This increases protection from changes by components that
            should not modify a particular session namespace, because they won't have easy access. However, limiting a
            namespace to a single instance may lead to more code or more complex code, as it removes access to the
            convient <code>$aNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('aNamespace');</code>, after the first intance has
            been created, as follows in the example below:
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Limiting to Single Instances</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    require_once 'Zend/Session.php';
    $authSpaceAccessor1 = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth');
    $authSpaceAccessor2 = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth', Zend_Session_Namespace::SINGLE_INSTANCE);
    $authSpaceAccessor1->foo = 'bar';
    assert($authSpaceAccessor2->foo, 'bar'); // passes
    doSomething($options, $authSpaceAccessor2); // pass the accessor to wherever it is needed
    .
    .
    .
    $aNamespaceObject = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth'); // this will throw an error
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            The second parameter in the constructor above will tell Zend_Session_Namespace that any future
            Zend_Session's that are instantiated with the 'Zend_Auth' namespace are not allowed, and will thus cause an
            exception. Since <code>new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth')</code> will not be allowed after the code
            above has been executed, the developer becomes responsible for storing the instance object
            (<code>$authSpaceAccessor2</code> in the example above) somewhere, if access to this session namespace is
            needed at a later time during the same request. For example, a developer may store the instance in a static
            variable, or pass it to other methods that might need access to this session namespace. Session locking (see
            above) provides a more convenient, and less burdensome approach to limiting access to namespaces.
        </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.modifyingarray">

        <title>Working with Arrays in Namespaces</title>

        <para>
            Modifying an array inside a namespace does not work. The simplest solution is to store arrays after all
            desired values have been set.
            <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/issues/browse/ZF-800">ZF-800</ulink>
            documents a known issue affecting many PHP applications using magic methods and arrays.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Known problem with arrays</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    $sessionNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Foo');
    $sessionNamespace->array = array();
    $sessionNamespace->array['testKey'] = 1; // nie działa przed PHP 5.2.1
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            If you need to modify the array after assigning it to a session namespace key, fetch the array, then
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Workaround: fetch, modify, save</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    $sessionNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Foo');
    $sessionNamespace->array = array('tree' => 'apple');
    $tmp = $sessionNamespace->array;
    $tmp['fruit'] = 'peach';
    $sessionNamespace->array = $tmp;
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>
            Alternatively, store an array containing a reference to the desired array, and then access it indirectly.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Workaround: store array containing reference</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    $myNamespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('mySpace');

    // works, even for broken versions of PHP
    $a = array(1,2,3);
    $myNamespace->someArray = array( & $a ) ;
    $a['foo'] = 'bar';
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.auth">

        <title>Using Sessions with Authentication</title>

        <para>
            If your authentication adapter for <code>Zend_Auth</code> returns a 
            result where the authorization identity is an object (not 
            recommended), instead of an array, then make sure to require your 
            authorization identity class definition before starting the session. 
            Instead, we recommend storing the authorization ids computed within 
            an authentication adapter inside a well-known key in a session 
            namespace. For example, the default behavior of <code>Zend_Auth</code> 
            places this in the 'storage' key of the 'Zend_Auth' namespace.
        </para>

        <para>
            If you tell <code>Zend_Auth</code> to not persist authentication 
            tokens in sessions, then you can manually store the authorization id 
            in the session namespace, in a well-known location in a session namespace of 
            your choice. Often, applications have specific needs about where to 
            store credentials used (if any) and "authorization" identity. 
            Applications often map authentication identities (e.g. usernames) to 
            authorization identities (e.g. a uniquely assigned integer) during 
            authentication, which would occur in the Zend_Auth authentication
            adapter's <code>authenticate()</code> method.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Przykład: Simplified access of authorization ids</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
    // pre-authentication request
    require_once 'Zend/Auth/Adapter/Digest.php';
    $adapter = new Zend_Auth_Adapter_Digest($filename, $realm, $username, $password);
    $result = $adapter->authenticate();
    require_once 'Zend/Session/Namespace.php';
    $namespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth');
    if ($result->isValid()) {
        $namespace->authorizationId = $result->getIdentity();
        $namespace->date = time();
    } else {
        $namespace->attempts++;
    }

    // subsequent requests
    require_once 'Zend/Session.php';
    Zend_Session::start();
    $namespace = new Zend_Session_Namespace('Zend_Auth');

    echo "Valid: ", (empty($namespace->authorizationId) ? 'No' : 'Yes'), "\n"';
    echo "Authorization / user Id: ", (empty($namespace->authorizationId)
        ? 'none' : print_r($namespace->authorizationId, true)), "\n"';
    echo "Authentication attempts: ", (empty($namespace->attempts)
        ? '0' : $namespace->attempts), "\n"';
    echo "Authenticated on: ",
        (empty($namespace->date) ? 'No' : date(DATE_ATOM, $namespace->date), "\n"';
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>
        
        <para>
            Authorization ids stored client-side are subject to privilege escalation vulnerabilities, if these ids are
            used and trusted by the server, unless, for example, the id is duplicated on the server-side (e.g. in the
            session) and then cross-checked with the authorization id claimed by the client for the in-effect session.
            We are differentiating between "authentication ids" (e.g. usernames) and "authorization ids" (e.g. user id
            #101 in the users DB table).
        </para>

        <para>
            The latter is not uncommon for performance reasons, such as helping select from a pool of servers caching
            session information to help solve chicken-and-egg problems. Often debates ensue about
            whether to use the real authorization id in the cookie, or some substitute that aids in mapping to the real
            authorization id (or session or server(s) holding the user's session/profile, etc.), as some system security
            architects wish to prevent true "DB primary keys" from escaping into the wild. These architects try and obtain some level
            of protection by obfuscation in the event of a SQL injection vulnerability in their system. Not everyone
            uses auto-increment strategies for authorization ids.
        </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.session.testing">

        <title>Użycie sesji z testami jednostkowymi</title>

        <para>
            The Zend Framework relies on PHPUnit to facilitate testing of itself. Many developers extend the existing
            suite of unit tests to cover the code in their applications. The exception
            "<emphasis role="strong">Zend_Session is currently marked as read-only</emphasis>" is thrown while
            performing unit tests, if any write-related methods are used after ending the session. However, unit tests
            using Zend_Session require extra attention, because closing (<code>Zend_Session::writeClose()</code>), or
            destroying a session (<code>Zend_Session::destroy()</code>) prevents any further setting or unsetting of
            keys in any Zend_Session_Namespace. This behavior is a direct result of the underlying ext/session mechanism
            and PHP's <code>session_destroy()</code> and <code>session_write_close()</code>, which has no "undo"
            mechanism to facilitate setup/teardown with unit tests.
        </para>

        <para>
            To work around this, see the unit test <code>testSetExpirationSeconds()</code> in
            <code>tests/Zend/Session/SessionTest.php and SessionTestHelper.php</code>, which make use of PHP's
            <code>exec()</code> to launch a separate process. The new process more accurately simulates a second,
            successive request from a browser. The separate process begins with a "clean" session, just like any PHP
            script execution for a web request. Also, any changes to <code>$_SESSION[]</code> made in the calling
            process become available to the child process, provided the parent closed the session before using
            <code>exec()</code>
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Użycie PHPUnit do testowania kodu używającego Zend_Session*</title>
<programlisting role="php">
<![CDATA[<?php
        // testowanie setExpirationSeconds()
        require 'tests/Zend/Session/SessionTestHelper.php'; // zobacz także plik SessionTest.php w trunk/
        $script = 'SessionTestHelper.php';
        $s = new Zend_Session_Namespace('space');
        $s->a = 'apple';
        $s->o = 'orange';
        $s->setExpirationSeconds(5);

        Zend_Session::regenerateId();
        $id = Zend_Session::getId();
        session_write_close(); // release session so process below can use it
        sleep(4); // not long enough for things to expire
        exec($script . "expireAll $id expireAll", $result);
        $result = $this->sortResult($result);
        $expect = ';a === apple;o === orange;p === pear';
        $this->assertTrue($result === $expect,
            "iteration over default Zend_Session namespace failed; expecting result === '$expect', but got '$result'");

        sleep(2); // long enough for things to expire (total of 6 seconds waiting, but expires in 5)
        exec($script . "expireAll $id expireAll", $result);
        $result = array_pop($result);
        $this->assertTrue($result === '',
            "iteration over default Zend_Session namespace failed; expecting result === '', but got '$result')");
        session_start(); // resume artificially suspended session

        // We could split this into a separate test, but actually, if anything leftover from above
        // contaminates the tests below, that is also a bug that we want to know about.
        $s = new Zend_Session_Namespace('expireGuava');
        $s->setExpirationSeconds(5, 'g'); // now try to expire only 1 of the keys in the namespace
        $s->g = 'guava';
        $s->p = 'peach';
        $s->p = 'plum';

        session_write_close(); // release session so process below can use it
        sleep(6); // not long enough for things to expire
        exec($script . "expireAll $id expireGuava", $result);
        $result = $this->sortResult($result);
        session_start(); // resume artificially suspended session
        $this->assertTrue($result === ';p === plum',
            "iteration over named Zend_Session namespace failed (result=$result)");
?>]]></programlisting>
        </example>

    </sect2>

</sect1>
