<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
]>
<!-- $Id: $ -->
<sect1 id="zend.translate.using">

    <title>Using translation Adapters</title>

    <para>
        The next step will be to use the adapter within your code. So let's look at a small example.
    </para>

    <para><programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[<?php
print "Example\n";
print "=======\n";
print "Here is line one\n";
print "Today is the " . date("d.m.Y") . "\n";
print "\n";
print "Fix language here is line two\n";
?>]]></programlisting>
    </para>    

    <para>
        You will probably write your code in your native language. Our example shows some output.
        Generally you will not only translate the output but also error or log messages.
    </para>

    <para>
        The next step will be to include Zend Translate into your existing code. Of course it will be
        much easier if you are writing your code already by using Zend Translate instead of changing 
        your code afterwards...
    </para>

    <para><programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[<?php
require_once("Zend/Translate.php");

$translate = new Zend_Translate('gettext', '/my/path/source-de.mo', 'de');
$translate->addTranslation('//my/path/fr-source.mo', 'fr');

print $translate->_("Example")."\n";
print "=======\n";
print $translate->_("Here is line one")."\n";
printf($translate->_("Today is the %1\$s") . "\n", date("d.m.Y"));
print "\n";

$translation->setLanguage('fr');
print $translate->_("Fix language here is line two") . "\n";
?>]]></programlisting>
    </para>    

    <para>
        Now lets get a deeper look into what has been done and how to integrate Zend Translate into your code.
    </para>

    <para>
        First of all you will have to create a new Translation Object and define the base adapter.

<programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[<?php
require_once("Zend/Translate.php");

$translate = new Zend_Translate('gettext', '/my/path/source-de.mo', 'de');
?>]]></programlisting>

        In our example we decided the <emphasis role="strong">Gettext Adapter</emphasis>.
        We will place our file <emphasis role="strong">source-de.mo</emphasis> into the directory 
        <emphasis role="strong">/my/path</emphasis>. The gettext file will have german translation 
        included. And we also added another language source for french.
    </para>

    <para>
        The next step is to wrap all strings which will be translated. The simplest approach is to have
        only simple strings or sentences like this:

<programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[<?php
print $translate->_("Example")."\n";
print "=======\n";
print $translate->_("Here is line one")."\n";
?>]]></programlisting>

        Of course some strings will not needed to be translated... a seperating line is always a seperated line,
        even in other languages.
    </para>

    <para>
        Having informations integrated into a translation string is also no big issue.
        
<programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[<?php
printf($translate->_("Today is the %1\$s") . "\n", date("d.m.Y"));
?>]]></programlisting>

        Instead of print use the printf function and exclude all informations with %1\$s parts.
        The first is %1\$s, the second %2\$s and so on. This way a translation can be done without knowing 
        the exact information. In our example the date is always the actual day, but the string can be translated
        without the knowledge of the actual day.
    </para>

    <para>
        Of course you can also use message id's instead of strings. In the above examples the message id's are
        identical with the strings. So we could also do it like this:

<programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[<?php
print $translate->_(1)."\n";
print "=======\n";
print $translate->_(2)."\n";
?>]]></programlisting>

        But doing so has several disadvantages.
    </para>

    <para>
        You will not be able to see what your code should output just by viewing your code.
    </para>

    <para>
        Also you will get problems if some strings are not translated. You always must imagine how
        translation works. First Zend Translate looks if the set language has a translation for the 
        given message id / string. If no translation string has been found it refers to the next lower 
        language as defined within Zend Locale. So <emphasis role="strong">de_AT</emphasis> will become
        <emphasis role="strong">de</emphasis> only. And if also for <emphasis role="strong">de</emphasis>
        there is no translation found the original message id will be returned. This way you will always
        have an output. Zend Translate will never throw an error or exception when translating strings.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="zend.translate.using.structure">

        <title>Translation Source structures</title>

        <para>
            Your next step will be to create the translation sources for the several languages you want to 
            translate to. Every adapter is created it's own way as described here. But there are some general
            feature which are relevant for all adapters.
        </para>

        <para>
            First of all you should know where to store your translation source files. With Zend_Translate you
            are not bundled to any restriction. The following structures are preferable:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Single structured source
                </para>

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
/application
/languages
  lang.en
  lang.de
/library
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Positive: All source files for every languages can be found in one directory. 
                    No splitting of related files.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Language structured source
                </para>

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
/application
/languages
  /en
    lang.en
    other.en
  /de
    lang.de
    other.de
/library
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Positive: Every language is based in one directory. Easy translation as only one directory 
                    has to be translated by a language team. Also the useage of multiple files is transparent.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Application structured source
                </para>

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
/application
  /languages
    lang.en
    lang.de
    other.en
    other.de
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Positive: All source files for every languages can be found in one directory. 
                    No splitting of related files.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Negative: Having multiple files for the same language is problematic.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Gettext structured source
                </para>

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
/languages
  /de
    /LC_MESSAGES
      lang.mo
      other.mo
  /en
    /LC_MESSAGES
      lang.mo
      other.mo
]]></programlisting>

                <para>
                    Positive: Old gettext sources can be used without changing structure.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Negative: Having sub-sub directories is for people which have not used gettext
                    before problematic.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                   File structured source
                </para>

                <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
/application
  /models
    mymodel.php
    mymodel.de
    mymodel.en
  /views
  /controllers
    mycontroller.de
/document_root
  /images
  /styles
  .htaccess
  index.php
  index.de
/library
  /Zend
]]></programlisting>
                <para>
                    Positive: Every file is realted to its own translation source.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Negative: Multiple small translation source files makes it harder to translate.
                    Also every file has to be added as translation source.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            Single structured and language structured source files are most useable for Zend_Translate.
        </para>

        <para>
            So now, that we know which structure we want to have, we should create our translation source files.
        </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.translate.using.source.array">

        <title>Creating array source files</title>

        <para>
            Array source files are just arrays. But you have to define them manually as there is no tool
            for this. But because they are so simple, it's the fastest way to look if your code works as
            expected and it's the best adapter to get started with translation business.
        </para>

        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
$english = array('message1' => 'message1',
                 'message2' => 'message2',
                 'message3' => 'message3');
$german = array('message1' => 'Nachricht1',
                'message2' => 'Nachricht2',
                'message3' => 'Nachricht3');

$translate = new Zend_Translate('array', $english, 'en');
$translate->addTranslation($deutsch, 'de');
]]></programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.translate.using.source.gettext">

        <title>Creating gettext source files</title>

        <para>
            Gettext source files are created by GNU's gettext library. There are several free tools avaiable 
            which can parse your code files and create the needed gettext source files. These files have the 
            ending <emphasis role="strong">*.mo</emphasis> and are binary files. A freeware tool for creating
            the files is for example poEdit (http://www.poedit.net). This tool also supports you for the
            translation process itself. 
        </para>

        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
// We expect that we have created the mo files and translated them
$translate = new Zend_Translate('gettext', 'path/to/english.mo', 'en');
$translate->addTranslation('path/to/german.mo', 'de');
]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            As you can see the adapters are used exactly the same way, with only just one small difference.
            We changed 'array' to 'gettext'... all other useages are exactly the same as with all other
            adapters. So with the gettext adapter you have no longer be aware of gettext's standard 
            directory structure, bindtextdomain and textdomain. Just give the path and filename to the adapter
            and that's it.
        </para>

        <note>
            <para>
                You should always use UTF-8 as source encoding. Otherwise you will have problems if you are 
                using two different source encodings. Expect you have one source file with ISO-8815-11 and
                one with CP815. But you can only set one encoding for your source file. So one of your languages
                will probably not be displayed correct. 
            </para>
            <para>
                UTF-8 is a portable format which supports all languages. So you will not have problems with 
                different languages by using it.
            </para>
        </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.translate.using.source.tmx">

        <title>Creating tmx source files</title>

        <para>
            Tmx source files are a new industry standard. They have the advantage to be xml files and
            so they are readable by every editor and of course human readable. You can eighter create TMX
            files manually or use a tool. But most tools are not freeware.
        </para>

        <para>
            Example tmx file:
        </para>

        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE tmx SYSTEM "tmx14.dtd">
<tmx version="1.4">
 <header creationtoolversion="1.0.0" datatype="winres" segtype="sentence" adminlang="en-us" srclang="de-at" o-tmf="abc" creationtool="XYZTool" >
 </header>
 <body>
  <tu tuid='message1'>
   <tuv xml:lang="de"><seg>Nachricht1</seg></tuv>
   <tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>message1</seg></tuv>
  </tu>
  <tu tuid='message2'>
   <tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>message2</seg></tuv>
   <tuv xml:lang="de"><seg>Nachricht2</seg></tuv>
  </tu>
]]></programlisting>

        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
$translate = new Zend_Translate('tmx', 'path/to/mytranslation.tmx', 'en');
// TMX can have several languages within one Tmx file.
]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Tmx files can have several languages within the same file. All other included languages
            will be added automatically, so you will not have to call addLanguage();
        </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.translate.using.source.csv">

        <title>Creating csv source files</title>

        <para>
            Csv source files are small and human readable. If your customers want to translate their own,
            you will probably use the csv adapter.
        </para>

        <para>
            Example csv file:
        </para>

        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
﻿#Example csv file
message1;Nachricht1
message2;Nachricht2
]]></programlisting>

        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
$translate = new Zend_Translate('csv', 'path/to/mytranslation.csv', 'de');
$translate->addTranslation('path/to/other.csv', 'fr');
]]></programlisting>
    </sect2>

</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
