<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
]>
<!-- $Id: $ -->
<sect1 id="zend.translate.introduction">

    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
        Zend_Translate is the answer of the Zend Framework to the problem of multilingual sites.
    </para>

    <para>
        Multilingual sites are having the problem that the content has to be translated into several languages and
        depending on the users language the proper content has to be displayed. PHP itself offers already several ways
        to handle such problems.
    </para>

    <para>
        Actual problems of PHP are:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                No API
            </para>
            <para>
                There is no API for the different source formats. The useage of gettext for example is for a beginner
                very complicated.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Only gettext and array native supported
            </para>
            <para>
                PHP itself offers only support for array or gettext. All other source formats have to be coded per hand,
                as there is no native support.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                No detection of the default language
            </para>
            <para>
                The default language of the user can not be detected without deeper knowledge of the beackgrounds for
                the different web browsers.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Gettext is not thread save
            </para>
            <para>
                PHP's gettext library is not tread save. So PHP's gettext library should not be used in a multithreaded
                environment. This is due to problems with gettext itself, not PHP, but it is an existing problem.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        Zend_Translate itself does not have these problems. This is why we announce anyone to use Zend_Translate instead
        of PHP's native functions. The benefits are:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Multiple source formats supported
            </para>
            <para>
                Multiple different source formats are supported within Zend_Translate. So when the format of the source
                files change from Gettext to Tmx the only thing to do is just change one line.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Threadsave gettext
            </para>
            <para>
                The gettext reader of Zend_Translate is threadsave. There will be no problems by using it in
                multithreaded environments.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Easy and generic API
            </para>
            <para>
                The API of Zend_Translate is very simple and supports only a hand full of functions. So it's easy to
                learn and easy to maintain. All source formats are handled the same way.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Detection of the users standard language
            </para>
            <para>
                The preferred language of the user accessing the site can be detected and used by Zend_Translate.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2 id="zend.translate.introduction.adapters">

        <title>Starting multilingual</title>

        <para>
            So let's get started with Multilingual business. What we want to do is translating our string
            output so the view produces the translated output. Otherwise we would have to write one view
            per every language, and no one would like to do this. Principially multilingual sites are very
            simple in their design. There are only 4 steps you would have to do...
        </para>

        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Decide which adaptor you want to use
                </para>
                <para>
                    Create your view and integrate Zend_Translate in your code
                </para>
                <para>
                    Create the source file from your code
                </para>
                <para>
                    Translate your source file to the wished language
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            We will guide you through all 4 steps so just read through the next few pages to create your
            own multilingual site.
        </para>

    </sect2>

</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
