<sect1 id="zend.date.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        With <code>Zend_Date</code> the Zend Framework offers a detailed and very simple API for
        date and time handling. It offers a large amount of features and possibilities which even
        take the standard PHP functions to a higher level.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The simple handling of time and date a required by each user. But it in reality it is never 
    	as simple as it seemed to be on the first glance.
    </para>
    <para>
    	The background is very simple. Dates as well as times are written differently in each 
    	country. Once the month is written at the first position, another time the day is written
    	first. 
    </para>
    <sect2 id="zend.date.possibilities">
        <title>Zend_Date possibilities</title>
        <para>
            Why should you use <code>Zend_Date</code> instead of the standard PHP functions?
        </para>
        <para>
            Well, among other things <code>Zend_Date</code> offers the following features which 
            extend the standard PHP scope:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Simple API
                </para>
                <para>
                    <code>Zend_Date</code> offers a very simple API which combines the best of
                    4 programming languages. It is possible, for example, to add or compare 2 times
                    within a single row. 
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Completely internationalized
                </para>
                <para>
                    All full and abbreviated names of months and days are supported for more than 
                    130 languages. Both at the input and the output of a date the day and month can
                    be written in the local languages.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Unlimited timestamps
                </para>
                <para>
                	Until release 5 PHP only supports 32bit timestamps. Since PHP 5.2 the support
                	partly rises tp 64bit timestamps. With Zend_Date unlimited timestamp will be
                	supported. Even very high values can be calculated. The only limit is the 
                	speed of the server.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Support for ISO_8601 date specifications
                </para>
                <para>
                	ISO_8601 date specifications are supported. Whereas even partial compliant 
                	ISO_8601 date specifications will be identified. These dates formats are
                	particularly used within databases. For example MsSQL and MySQL dates can be
                	mentioned here. They differ a little from each other but both are supported.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Calculate sunrise and sunset
                </para>
                <para>
                	For any place and day the times for sunrise and sunset can be displayed.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->