<sect1 id="zend.openid.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        <code>Zend_OpenId</code> is a Zend Framework componet that provides
        simple API to build OpenID-enabled sites and identity providers.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="zend.openid.introduction.what">
        <title>What is OpenID?</title>
        <para>
            OpenID is a set of protocols for user-centric digital identities.
            They allow to create identity online on some identity provider and
            use it anywhere OpenID is supported. Using OpenID-enabled sites,
            web users do not need to remember traditional authentication tokens
            such as username and password. All OpenID-enabled sites accepts the
            single OpenID identity. This identity is typically a URL. It may be
            the URL of the user's personal page, blog or other resource that
            may provide additional information about them. No more need for
            many passwords and different user names - just one identifier for
            all Internet services. OpenID is an open, decentralized, and free
            user centric solution. A user may choose which OpenID provider to
            use, or even create their own personal identity server. No central
            authority must approve or register OpenID-enabled sites or
            indentity providers.
        </para>

        <para>
            For more information about OpenID visit
            <ulink url="http://www.openid.org/">OpenID official site</ulink>
            and look into
            <ulink url="http://www.openidbook.com/">OpenID Book by Rafeeq Rehman</ulink>.
        </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.openid.introduction.how">
        <title>How it works?</title>
        <para>
            The main purpose of <code>Zend_OpenId</code> components is
            implementing an OpenID authentication protocol described in the
            following diagram:
        </para>

        <para>
            <inlinegraphic width="559" scale="100" align="center" valign="middle"
                fileref="figures/zend.openid.protocol.jpg" format="JPEG" />
        </para>

        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                The authentication is initiated by end-user, who passes their
                OpenID identifier to an OpenID consumer through User-Agent.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                OpenID consumer performs normalization of user-supplied
                identifier, and discovery on it. As result it get claimed
                identifier, OpenID provider URL and OpenID protocol version.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                OpenID client establishes an optional association with server
                using Diffie-Hellman keys. As result both parties get common
                shared secret that is used for signing and verification of the
                following messages. 
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                OpenID consumer redirects User-Agent to OpenID provider URL
                with OpenID authentication request. 
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                OpenID Provider checks if user-Agent is already authenticated
                and offers to do so if need.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                The end user enters necessary password. 
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                OpenID Provider checks if it allowed to pass user identity to
                given consumer, and asks user if need.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                The end user allows or disallows passing his identity.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                OpenID Provider redirects User-Agent back to OpenID consumer
                with authentication approved or failed request.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                The OpenID consumer verifies the information received from
                provider by using shared secret got on step 3 or by sending
                additional direct request to OpenID proider. 
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.openid.introduction.standards">
        <title>Supported Standards</title>
        <para>
            <code>Zend_OpenId</code> component conforms to the following
            standards:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                OpenID Authentication protocol version 1.1
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                OpenID Authentication protocol version 2.0 draf 11
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                OpenID Simple Registration Extension version 1.0
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                OpenID Simple Registration Extension version 1.1 draft 1
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->