<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
]>
<!-- $Id: $ -->
<sect1 id="zend.translate.adapter">

    <title>Adapters for Zend_Translate</title>

    <para>
        Zend_Translate can handle different adapters for translation. Each adapter has it's own pros and cons.
        Here you can find a comprehensive list of all supported adapters for translation source files.
    </para>

    <table>
        <title>Adapters for Zend_Translate</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
                <row>
                    <entry>Adapter</entry>
                    <entry>Description</entry>
                    <entry>Useage</entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>Array</entry>
                    <entry>Use php arrays</entry>
                    <entry>Small pages, simplest useage, only for programmers</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Csv</entry>
                    <entry>Use comma seperated (*.csv/*.txt) files</entry>
                    <entry>Simple text file format, very fast, possible problems with unicode characters</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Gettext</entry>
                    <entry>Use binary gettext (*.mo) files</entry>
                    <entry>Gnu standard for linux, very fast, threadsave, needs tools for translation</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Tmx</entry>
                    <entry>Use tmx (*.tmx) files</entry>
                    <entry>Industry standard for inter application translation, xml format, human readable</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Others</entry>
                    <entry>*.xliff, *.sql, *.tbx, *.qt</entry>
                    <entry>Different other adapters are supposed to be implemented in the future but not ready for now</entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table>

    <sect2 id="zend.translate.adapter.decision">

        <title>How to decide which translation adapter to use</title>

        <para>
            First of all you should decide which Adapter you want to use for Zend_Translate.
            Most times your Customer will decide for you but if you are in the Position to to this yourself,
            we give you some hints to simplify you your decision.
        </para>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.array">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Array</title>

            <para>
                The Array Adapter is the Adapter which is simplest to use for Programmers.
                But when you have much translation strings or much languages you should think about another
                Adapter. If you have for example 5000 translation strings the Array Adapter is posibly 
                not the best choice for you.
            </para>

            <para>
                You should only use this Adapter for small sites with only a handfull languages and if you 
                or your programmer team does translations your own.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.csv">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Csv</title>

            <para>
                The Csv Adapter is the Adapter which is simplest to use for Customers.
                Csv files are readable by standard text editors but you will have problems when you
                want to use it with utf8 charactersets.
            </para>

            <para>
                You should only use this Adapter if your customer want to do translations himself.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.gettext">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Gettext</title>

            <para>
                The Gettext Adapter is the Adapter which is used most of times. Gettext is a translation source
                format which was introduced by Gnu and nowadays used worldwide. It is not human readable but there
                are several freeware tools (f.e. POEdit) out there which are very helpfull. The Zend Framework
                is not related to PHP's gettext extension. You can use the gettext adapter even if you do not have
                the extension installed. Also the Adapter is threadsave and the extension is not for now.
            </para>

            <para>
                Most people will use this adapter. With the avaiable tools also professional translation is 
                very simple. But this format is not readable without tools.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.tmx">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Tmx</title>

            <para>
                The Tmx Adapter is the Adapter which will be used by most customers which have multiple systems
                which use the same translation source or when the translation source have to be system independent.
                Tmx is a XML file based format, which is announced to be the next industry standard. Xml files are
                human readable but the parsing is not that fast as with gettext files.
            </para>

            <para>
                Most medium to big sized companys will use this adapter. The files are human readable and system
                independent.
            </para>
        </sect3>

    </sect2>

</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
