<sect1 id="zend.progressbar">
    <title>Zend_ProgressBar</title>
    
    <sect2 id="zend.progressbar.introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
	        <code>Zend_ProgressBar</code> is a component to create and update
	        progressbars in different enviroments. It consists of a single
	        backend, which outputs the progress through one of the multiple
	        adapters. On every update, it takes an absolute value and optionally
	        a status message, and then calls the adapter with some precalculated
	        values like percentage and estimated time left.
        </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.progressbar.basic">
        <title>Basic usage of Zend_Progressbar</title>
        <para>
            <code>Zend_ProgressBar</code> is quite easy in it's usage. You
            simply create a new instance of Zend_Progressbar, defining a
            min- and a max-value, and choose an adapter to output the data. If
            you want to process a file, you would do something like:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
$progressBar = new Zend_ProgressBar(0, $fileSize, $adapter);

while (!feof($fp)) {
    // Do something
    
    $progressBar->update($currentByteCount);
}

$progressBar->finish();
]]>
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>
            In the first step, an instance of <code>Zend_ProgressBar</code> is
            created, with a min-value of 0, a max-value of the total filesize
            and a specific adapter. Then a file is processed and in every loop
            the progressbar is updated with the current byte count. At the end
            of the loop, the progressbar status is set to finished.  
        </para>
        <para>
            <code>Zend_ProgressBar</code> also has a refresh() method which just
            recalculates ETA and updates the adapter. This is useful when there
            is no data update but you want the progressbar to be updated.
        </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.progressbar.adapters">
        <title>Standard adapters</title>
	    <para>
	        <code>Zend_ProgressBar</code> comes with the following two adapters:
	        
	        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
	            <listitem><para><xref linkend="zend.progressbar.adapter.console" /></para></listitem>
	            <listitem><para><xref linkend="zend.progressbar.adapter.jspush" /></para></listitem>
	        </itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	    
        <xi:include href="Zend_Progressbar_Adapter_Console.xml" />
        <xi:include href="Zend_Progressbar_Adapter_JsPush.xml" />
    </sect2>
</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
