<sect1 id="zend.soap.autodiscovery.introduction">
    <title>AutoDiscovery. Introduction</title>
    <para>
        SOAP functionality implemented within Zend Framework is intended to make all steps
        required for SOAP communications more simple.
    </para>

    <para>
        SOAP is language independent protocol. So it may be used not only for PHP-to-PHP communications.
    </para>
    
    <para>
        There are three configurations for SOAP applications where Zend Framework may be utilized:
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>SOAP server PHP application &lt;---&gt; SOAP client PHP application</simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>SOAP server non-PHP application &lt;---&gt; SOAP client PHP application</simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>SOAP server PHP application &lt;---&gt; SOAP client non-PHP application</simpara>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>
        We always have to know, which functionality is provided by SOAP server to operate with it.
        <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/wsdl">WSDL</ulink> is used to describe network service API
        in details.  
    </para>

    <para>
        WSDL language is complex enough (see <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/wsdl">http://www.w3.org/TR/wsdl</ulink> 
        for the details). So it's difficult to prepare correct WSDL description.      
    </para>
    
    <para>
        Another problem is synchronizing changes in network service API with already existing WSDL.      
    </para>

    <para>
        Both these problem may be solved by WSDL autogeneration. A prerequisite for this is a SOAP server autodiscovery.
        It constructs object similar to object used in SOAP server application, extracts necessary information and generates 
        correct WSDL using this information. 
    </para>

    <para>
        There are two ways for using Zend Framework for SOAP server application:     
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use separated class.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use set of functions</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
        Both methods are supported by Zend Framework Autodiscovery functionality. 
    </para>

    <para>
        Zend_Soap_AutoDiscovery class also supports datatypes mapping from PHP to <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/">XSD types</ulink>. 
    </para>


    <para>
        Here is an example of common usage of the autodiscovery functionality:
        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[
class My_SoapServer_Class {
...
}

$autodiscover = new Zend_Soap_AutoDiscover();
$autodiscover->setClass('My_SoapServer_Class');
$autodiscover->handle();]]></programlisting>
    </para>
</sect1>
