<sect1 id="zend.translate.adapter">

    <title>Adapters for Zend_Translate</title>

    <para>
        Zend_Translate can handle different adapters for translation.
        Each adapter has its own advantages and disadvantages.
        Below is a comprehensive list of all supported adapters for
        translation source files.
    </para>

    <table id="zend.translate.adapter.table">
        <title>Adapters for Zend_Translate</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
                <row>
                    <entry>Adapter</entry>
                    <entry>Description</entry>
                    <entry>Usage</entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>Array</entry>
                    <entry>Use php arrays</entry>
                    <entry>Small pages; simplest usage; only for programmers</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Csv</entry>
                    <entry>Use comma seperated (*.csv/*.txt) files</entry>
                    <entry>Simple text file format; very fast; possible problems with unicode characters</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Gettext</entry>
                    <entry>Use binary gettext (*.mo) files</entry>
                    <entry>GNU standard for linux; very fast; thread-safe; needs tools for translation</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>TMX</entry>
                    <entry>Use tmx (*.tmx/*.xml) files</entry>
                    <entry>Industry standard for inter application translation; XML format; human readable</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>QT</entry>
                    <entry>Use qt linguist (*.ts) files</entry>
                    <entry>Cross platform application framework; XML format; human readable</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>XLIFF</entry>
                    <entry>Use xliff (*.xliff/*.xml) files</entry>
                    <entry>A simpler format as TMX but related to it; XML format; human readable</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Others</entry>
                    <entry>*.sql, *.tbx, *.tm</entry>
                    <entry>Different other adapters may be implemented in the future</entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table>

    <sect2 id="zend.translate.adapter.decision">

        <title>How to decide which translation adapter to use</title>

        <para>
            You should decide which Adapter you want to use for Zend_Translate.
            Frequently, external criteria such as a project requirement or
            a customer requirement determines this for you, but if you are in
            the position to do this yourself, the following hints may simplify
            your decision.
        </para>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.array">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Array</title>

            <para>
                The Array Adapter is the Adapter which is simplest to use for
                programmers.
                But when you have numerous translation strings or many
                languages you should think about another Adapter.
                For example, if you have 5000 translation strings,
                the Array Adapter is possibly not the best choice for you.
            </para>

            <para>
                You should only use this Adapter for small sites with a handful
                of languages, and if you or your programmer team creates the
                translations yourselves.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.csv">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Csv</title>

            <para>
                The Csv Adapter is the Adapter which is simplest to use for
                customers.
                CSV files are readable by standard text editors, but
                text editors often do not support utf8 character sets.
            </para>

            <para>
                You should only use this Adapter if your customer wants to do
                translations himself.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.gettext">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Gettext</title>

            <para>
                The Gettext Adapter is the Adapter which is used most
                frequently.  Gettext is a translation source format which was
                introduced by GNU, and is now used worldwide.
                It is not human readable, but there are several freeware tools
                (for instance, <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/poedit/">POEdit</ulink>), which are very helpful.
                The Zend_Translate Gettext Adapter is not implemented using
                PHP's gettext extension.
                You can use the Gettext Adapter even if you do not have
                the PHP gettext extension installed.
                Also the Adapter is thread-safe and the PHP gettext extension
                is currently not thread-safe.
            </para>

            <para>
                Most people will use this adapter.
                With the available tools, professional translation is
                very simple.  But gettext data are is stored in a
                machine-readable format, which is not readable without tools.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.tmx">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Tmx</title>

            <para>
                The Tmx Adapter is the Adapter which will be used by most
                customers which have multiple systems which use the same
                translation source, or when the translation source must be
                system-independent.
                TMX is a XML file based format, which is announced to be the
                next industry standard.
                XML files are human-readable, but the parsing is not as fast
                as with gettext files.
            </para>

            <para>
                Most medium to large companies use this adapter.
                The files are human readable and system-independent.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.qt">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Qt</title>

            <para>
                The Qt Adapter is for all customers which have TS files as their
                translation source which are made by QtLinguist.
                QT is a XML file based format.
                XML files are human-readable, but the parsing is not as fast
                as with gettext files.
            </para>

            <para>
                Several big players have build software upon the QT framework.
                The files are human readable and system-independent.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="zend.translate.adapter.xliff">

            <title>Zend_Translate_Adapter_Xliff</title>

            <para>
                The Xliff Adapter is the Adapter which will be used by most
                customers which want to have XML files but do not have tools
                for TMX.
                XLIFF is a XML file based format, which is related to TMX but
                simpler as it does not support all possibilities of it.
                XML files are human-readable, but the parsing is not as fast
                as with gettext files.
            </para>

            <para>
                Most medium companies use this adapter.
                The files are human readable and system-independent.
            </para>
        </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.translate.adapter.selfwritten">

        <title>Integrate self written Adapters</title>

        <para>
            Zend_Translate allows you to integrate and use self written Adapter
            classes. They can be used like the standard Adapter classes which
            are already included within Zend_Translate.
        </para>

        <para>
            Any adapter class you want to use with Zend_Translate must be a subclass
            of Zend_Translate_Adapter. Zend_Translate_Adapter is an abstract class
            which already defines all what is needed for translation. What has to be
            done by you, is the definition of the reader for translation datas.
        </para>

        <para>
            The useage of the prefix "Zend" should be limited to the Zend_Framework.
            If you extend Zend_Translate with your own adapter, you should name it
            like "Company_Translate_Adapter_MyFormat". The following code shows an
            example of how a self written adapter class could be implemented:
        </para>

        <programlisting role="php"><![CDATA[<?php
require_once 'Zend/Translate.php';

try {
    $translate = new Zend_Translate('Company_Translate_Adapter_MyFormat', '/path/to/translate.xx', 'en', array('myoption' => 'myvalue'));
} catch (Exception $e) {
    // File not found, no adapter class...
    // General failure
}]]>
        </programlisting>

    </sect2>

</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
