<sect1 id="zend.openid.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        <code>Zend_OpenId</code> is a Zend Framework component that provides a
        simple API for building OpenID-enabled sites and identity providers.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="zend.openid.introduction.what">
        <title>What is OpenID?</title>
        <para>
            OpenID is a set of protocols for user-centric digital identities.
            These protocols allow to create an identity online, using an identity
            provider. This identity can be used anywhere that OpenID is supported.
            Using OpenID-enabled sites, web users do not need to remember traditional
            authentication tokens such as username and password. All OpenID-enabled
            sites accept a single OpenID identity. This identity is typically a URL.
            It may be the URL of the user's personal page, blog or other resource that
            may provide additional information about them. No more need for many
            passwords and different user names - just one identifier for all Internet
            services. OpenID is an open, decentralized, and free user centric
            solution. A user may choose which OpenID provider to use, or even create
            their own personal identity server. No central authority is needed to
            approve or register OpenID-enabled sites or identity providers.
        </para>

        <para>
            For more information about OpenID visit <ulink url="http://www.openid.net/">OpenID official site</ulink>
            and look into the <ulink url="http://www.openidbook.com/">OpenID Book by Rafeeq
            Rehman</ulink>.
        </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.openid.introduction.how">
        <title>How Does it Work?</title>
        <para>
            The main purpose of the <code>Zend_OpenId</code> components is to
            implement an OpenID authentication protocol as described in the following
            diagram:
        </para>

        <para>
            <inlinegraphic align="center" fileref="figures/zend.openid.protocol.jpg" format="JPEG" scale="100" valign="middle" width="559" />
        </para>

        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Authentication is initiated by the end-user, who passes their
                    OpenID identifier to the OpenID consumer through a User-Agent.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The OpenID consumer performs normalization of the user-supplied
                    identifier, and discovery on it. As result, it gets the following:
                    a claimed identifier, OpenID provider URL and an OpenID protocol
                    version.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The OpenID client establishes an optional association with the
                    server using Diffie-Hellman keys. As a result, both parties get
                    a common "shared secret" that is used for signing and verification
                    of the following (subsequent) messages.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The OpenID consumer redirects the User-Agent to the OpenID
                    provider's URL with an OpenID authentication request.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The OpenID Provider checks if the user-Agent is already
                    authenticated and offers to do so if needed.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The end user enters the required password.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The OpenID Provider checks if it is allowed to pass the user
                    identity to the given consumer, and asks the user if needed.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The end user allows or disallows passing his identity.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The OpenID Provider redirects the User-Agent back to the OpenID
                    consumer with an "authentication approved" or "failed" request.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The OpenID consumer verifies the information received from the
                    provider by using the "shared secret" it got on step 3 or by
                    sending additional direct request to the OpenID provider.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.openid.introduction.structure">
        <title>Zend_OpenId Structure</title>
        <para>
            <code>Zend_OpenId</code> consists of two sub packages. The first one
            is <code>Zend_OpenId_Consumer</code> for developing OpenID-enabled sites
            and the second <code>Zend_OpenId_Provider</code> for developing OpenID
            servers. They are completely independent of each other and may be used
            separately.
        </para>

        <para>
            The only common parts of these sub packages are the OpenID Simple
            Registration Extension implemented by
            <code>Zend_OpenId_Extension_Sreg</code> class and the set of utility
            functions implemented by <code>Zend_OpenId</code> class.
        </para>

        <note>
            <para>
                <code>Zend_OpenId</code> takes advantage of the <ulink url="http://php.net/gmp">GMP extension</ulink>,
                where available. Consider enabling the GMP extension for better performance when using
                <code>Zend_OpenId</code>.
            </para>
        </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zend.openid.introduction.standards">
        <title>Supported Standards</title>
        <para>
            The <code>Zend_OpenId</code> component conforms to the following
            standards:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    OpenID Authentication protocol version 1.1
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    OpenID Authentication protocol version 2.0 draft 11
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    OpenID Simple Registration Extension version 1.0
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    OpenID Simple Registration Extension version 1.1 draft 1
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
<!--
vim:se ts=4 sw=4 et:
-->
