<sect1 id="introduction.installation">

    <title>התקנה</title>

    <para>
        ראו את <link linkend="requirements">נספח דרישות המערכת</link> לרשימה מלאה של כל האלמנטים הדרושים לשימוש ב Zend Framework.
    </para>

    <para>
        התקנת המערכת של Zend Framework הינה קלה ומהירה. לאחר שהורדתם וחלצתם את הקבצים של ה framework , כדי לכם להוסיף את תיקית הספריה של Zend
        /library לתיקיה הראשית של האפליקציה שהנכם מתכנתים. כמו כן רצוי להעתיק את כל התוכן של הספריה אל מקום נוסף במחשב/תיקית שיתוף שיהיה ניתן לגשת אליה בקלות יותר.
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/download/latest">הורידו את הגרסא היציבה האחרונה של המערכת.</ulink>
                    הגרסא זמינה בשני סוגי פורמטים <code>.zip</code> ו <code>.tar.gz</code>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/download/snapshot">הורד את הגרסא 'הלילית' האחרונה</ulink> 
                    לאלו מכם שרוצים לנסות ולהשתתך בתהליך הבדיקות של המערכת, ניתן להוריד את גרסאת הפיתוח האחרונה ישירות מה SVN של המערכת.
                     גרסאות הפיתוח מגיעות עם הדוקומנטציה של המערכת באנגלית בלבד או בכל השפות. אם גם אתה רוצה להשתתף בפיתוח המערכת, תצטרך לשקלו שימוש ב subversion (SVN) לניהול קבצים.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Using a <ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org">Subversion</ulink> (SVN) client. Zend Framework
                    is open source software, and the Subversion repository used for its development is publicly
                    available. Consider using SVN to get Zend Framework if you already use SVN for your
                    application development, want to contribute back to the framework, or need to upgrade your
                    framework version more often than releases occur.
                </para>
                <para>
                    <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.export.html">Exporting</ulink> is
                    useful if you want to get a particular framework revision without the <code>.svn</code>
                    directories as created in a working copy.
                </para>
                <para>
                    <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.checkout.html">Check out a
                    working copy</ulink> if you want contribute to Zend Framework, a working copy can
                    be updated any time with
                    <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.update.html"><code>svn
                    update</code></ulink> and changes can be commited to our SVN repository with the <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.ref.svn.c.commit.html"><code>svn
                    commit</code></ulink> command.
                </para>
                <para>
                    An <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.advanced.externals.html">externals
                    definition</ulink> is quite convenient for developers already using SVN to manage their
                    application's working copies.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The URL for the trunk of the Zend Framework SVN repository is:
                    <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/standard/trunk">http://framework.zend.com/svn/framework/standard/trunk</ulink>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
        Once you have a copy of Zend Framework available, your application needs to be able to access the
        framework classes. Though there are
        <ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/configuration.changes.php">
        several ways to achieve this</ulink>, your PHP
        <ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/ini.core.php#ini.include-path"><code>include_path</code></ulink>
        needs to contain the path to the Zend Framework library.
    </para>

    <para>
        Zend provides a <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/docs/quickstart">QuickStart</ulink> to get you up and running
        as quickly as possible. This is an excellent way to begin learning about the framework with an emphasis
        on real world examples that you can build upon.
    </para>

    <para>
        Since Zend Framework components are loosely coupled, you may use a somewhat unique combination of them in your
        own applications. The following chapters provide a comprehensive reference to Zend Framework on a component-by-component
        basis.
    </para>

</sect1>
